## Heather Salvador

(951) 906-9474 | hsalv001@gmail.com | Linkedin @HeatherSalvador | Website: www.smathaudhu.com/heather-salvador/

### — MECHANICAL ENGINEER —

Mechanical engineer and materials science engineer with five years of experience in the aerospace and manufacturing industry, including project management, working directly with key customers, and supervisory responsibilities. Five years as a researcher under the advisement of Dr. Suveen Mathaudhu, working in a research and development environment specific to experimental design, scientific evaluation, and science communication relating to processing-property relationships in structural metals.

### EDUCATION =

PH.D. MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

University of California, Riverside Advisor: Dr. Suveen Mathaudhu June 2016 – July 2021 (estimated)

M.S. MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

*University of California, Riverside* Course-based program

Riverside, CA
October 2011 – June 2012

Riverside, CA

**B.S. MECHANICAL ENGINEERING** 

University of California, Riverside

Riverside, CA October 2007 – June 2011

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

RESEARCHER

UC Riverside, Mathaudhu Lab

Riverside, CA

[une 2016 - present

Required to understand the background science and previous research completed for each project, develop experiments with the goal of expanding scientific knowledge, present key research results, publish results in scientific journals, and mentor undergraduate students.

The main projects worked on during my tenure include the processing and characterization of:

- Gradient microstructures in Cu to study radiation tolerance fundamentals along various length scales
- Magnesium-based metal-matrix composite using powder metallurgy and densification to study the effect of yttrium hydride ceramic reinforcement on microstructural changes and resulting properties
- Dual phase magnesium-lithium alloys to determine the effect of processing pressure on resulting properties.

#### MANUFACTURING SUPERVISOR

VACCO Industries

South El Monte, CA

*June 2014 – April 2016* 

Oversaw and participated in the design and build of an assembly and test facility for space launch valve production. Responsible for hiring and training cleanroom-level technicians. Initiated cross-team collaboration and management to ensure on-time production.

Notable achievements include the development of a new assembly and test facility for a new product line, initiation of production meetings with cross-functional teams to increase communication, the hiring and training of skilled technicians, and developed comprehensive assembly and test charts capable of determining resources required for timely production on a new product line.

PROJECT ENGINEER

VACCO Industries

South El Monte, CA

June 2012 – June 2014

Managed the design development and testing of a space launch system valve, prepared manufacturing paperwork, and facilitated seamless transfer to production for delivery according to a customer-set schedule.

Notable achievements include the design of a lever for a space-level valve, production of a CAD model animations of valve operations, and the build and testing of a development unit for validation.

GKN Aerospace

*June 2011 – December 2011* 

Audited manufacturing paperwork, tracked and moved open quality incidents to closure, and worked with inspectors to standardize and improve inspection processes. Key achievements include the development of a standardized inspection instruction with accompanying visual work instruction

#### — TEACHING EXPERIENCE =

#### ABET COORDINATOR

Riverside, CA

UC Riverside, Mechanical Engineering Department

April 2017 - present

Collect and manage documentation for all mechanical engineering courses to demonstrate compliance with the accreditation requirements.

#### MECHANICAL ENGINEERING MODELING AND ANALYSIS

Riverside, CA

UC Riverside, Mechanical Engineering Department

January – March 2021

Teaching assistant responsible for teaching review sessions, grading student work, and providing individual student help relating to the course material: descriptive and inferential statistics, sampling and bootstrapping, fitting linear and nonlinear models to observed data, interpolation, numerical differentiation and integration, and solution of ordinary differential equations.

#### INTRODUCTION TO ENGINEERING COMPUTATION

Riverside, CA

UC Riverside, Mechanical Engineering Department

June – July 2020

Teaching assistant responsible for providing student guidance in MATLAB programming as applied to scripts, functions, input/outputs, two- and three-dimensional graphics, and elementary numerical analysis.

SENIOR DESIGN

Riverside, CA

UC Riverside, Mechanical Engineering Department

March - June 2020

Teaching assistant responsible for providing feedback on writing technical reports and professional presentations of student group design project.

#### MECHANICAL BEHAVIOR OF MATERIALS

Riverside, CA

UC Riverside, Mechanical Engineering Department

October – December 2016

Teaching assistant responsible for teaching review sessions, grading student work, and managing laboratory sessions relating to the course material: fundamental mechanisms of deformation and failure of metals, ceramics, polymers, composite materials, electronic and electronic materials. Structural design and materials selection.

#### = PUBLICATIONS =

[YH2 MMC TITLE]

In Preparation

Materials Characterization

Heather Salvador, Christian Roach, Suveen Mathaudhu

[CU PAPER]

In Preparation

Journal

Heather Salvador, Christian Roach, Suveen Mathaudhu

AUSFORMING AND TEMPERING OF A NOVELULTRA-HIGH STRENGTH STEEL

Submitted

Journal?

Yiwei Sun, Johny Quan, Heather Salvador, Jeffrey Lin, Thomas Kozmel, Suveen Mathaudhu

= PRESENTATIONS =

### RADIATION TOLERANCE OF GRADIENT GRAIN-STRUCTURED COPPER PROCESSED BY SURFACE MECHANICAL ATTRITION TREATMENT (POSTER)

February 2020

TMS Annual Meeting

Heather Salvador, Yiwei Sun, Trevor Clark, Khalid Hattar, Sina Shahrezaei, Suveen Mathaudhu

### GRAIN BOUNDARY PINNING BY YH2 PARTICLES IN MAGNESIUM PROCESSED BY CRYOMILLING AND SPARK PLASMA SINTERING (POSTER)

July 2019

Gordon Research Conference – Physical Metallurgy

Speaker Heather Salvador, Christian Roach, Suveen Mathaudhu

### GRAIN BOUNDARY PINNING BY YH2 PARTICLES IN MAGNESIUM PROCESSED BY CRYOMILLING AND SPARK PLASMA SINTERING (PRESENTATION & POSTER)

**June 2019** 

POWDERMET / AMPM Annual Meeting

Speaker Heather Salvador, Christian Roach, Suveen Mathaudhu

### EFFECT OF LOCAL STRESS ON FAULT FORMATION AND PROPAGATION WITHIN HCP MATERIALS (PRESENTATION)

March 2018

TMS Annual Meeting

Speaker Heather Salvador, Suveen Mathaudhu

### ROLE OF TEXTURE IN STRENGTHENING OF A MG-RE ALLOY WITH NANO-SPACED STACKING FAULTS (PRESENTATION)

May 2017

Mechanical Engineering Graduate Student Association Research Symposium Speaker Heather Salvador, Suveen Mathaudhu

### TEXTURAL CONTRIBUTIONS TO STRENGTHENING IN A MG-RE ALLOY WITH NANO-SPACED STACKING FAULTS (POSTER)

March 2017

TMS Annual Meeting

Heather Salvador, Vishnu Bhattacharyya, Yuntian Zhu, Sean Agnew, Suveen Mathaudhu

#### - TECHNICAL SKILLS ----

#### METALLURGICAL SAMPLE PROCESSING & PREPARATION

Laboratory-scale hot rolling, spark plasma sintering, heat treatment and quenching. Sample sectioning, mechanical polishing, electropolishing, electroless plating, and etching.

#### MICROSTRUCTURAL CHARACTERIZATION

Focused ion beam (FIB), scanning electron microscopy (SEM), energy dispersive spectroscopy (EDS), x-ray diffraction (XRD), transmission electron microscopy (TEM)

#### MECHANICAL PROPERTIES CHARACTERIZATION

Micro-hardness indentation, nano-hardness indentation, tension testing

**SOFTWARE** 

Origin, Matlab, SolidWorks, AutoCAD Inventor

### = AWARDS & CERTIFICATES ======

**FELLOW** 

Graduate Assistance in Areas of National Need

2019 - 2021

SCIENCE TO POLICY CERTIFICATE

Science to Policy Program at UC Riverside

June 2020

**GRANT RECIPIENT** 

**POWDERMET/AMPM Conference** National Science Foundation *June 2019* 

# 3RD POSTER COMPETITION

ASM Los Angeles Chapter

Student Night May 2016

### OUTREACH & VOLUNTEERING=

PRESENTATION JUDGE

Materials Science and Engineering Program at UC Riverside

Senior Design Presentations

March 2020

**ACTIVITY LEADER** 

Riverside County Office of Education

**Next Generation Science Standards** 

February 2020

LAB TOUR LEADER

Bourns College of Engineering at UC Riverside

Engineering 'R Future
October 2019

**GROUP LEADER** 

Society of Women Engineers at UC Riverside

Networking Night
November 2018

**ACTIVITY LEADER** 

Riverside Department of Education

Science and Engineering Fair

October 2018

**ACTIVITY LEADER** 

Hillcrest High School Science Night

Hillcrest High School Science Night

May 2018

LAB TOUR LEADER

Bourns College of Engineering at UC Riverside

Chaffey College Tour

August 2017

LAB TOUR LEADER

Bourns College of Engineering at UC Riverside

Ramona High School Tour

August 2017

1 11/3/101 2017

LAB TOUR LEADER

Bourns College of Engineering at UC Riverside

Riverside STEM Academy Tour July 2017

**VOLUNTEER SPEAKER** 

Society of Women Engineers at UC Riverside

Graduate Student Panel

May 2017

**ACTIVITY LEADER** 

Hillcrest High School Science Night

Hillcrest High School Science Night

May 2017

**ACTIVITY LEADER** 

Society of Women Engineers at UC Riverside

**Bourns Engineering Day** 

April 2017

RESEARCH GROUP REPRESENTATIVE

Society of Women Engineers at UC Riverside

Research Networking Night

February 2017

ACTIVITY DEMONSTRATION AND ROUNDTABLE DISCUSSION

Mathaudhu Lab Group

Norco Community College

November 2016

**VOLUNTEER SPEAKER** 

Engineers without Borders at UC Riverside

Graduate School Panel
November 2016

**ACTIVITY LEADER** 

Mathaudhu Lab Group

Riverside Science Fair Expo

October 2016

**ACTIVITY LEADER** 

Mathaudhu Lah Group

**USA STEM Festival** 

April 2016

**SPEAKER** 

Society of Women Engineers at UC Riverside

Research Networking Night May 2015

INDUSTRY REPRESENTATIVE

Society of Women Engineers at UC Riverside

**Evening with Industry Networking Event** 

Yearly 2013 - 2015

**VOLUNTEER** 

**ORGANIZER** 

Society of Women Engineers at UC Riverside

**Engineering Day** Yearly 2012 - 2015

Science and Engineering Fair

April 2011

April 2011

SCIENCE FAIR JUDGE

Riverside County Office of Education

**Engineering Day** 

Society of Women Engineers at UC Riverside

ACTIVITY ORGANIZER

Summer Autism Camp *June 2010* 

UC Riverside Autism Center

Engineering Day

**ORGANIZER** Society of Women Engineers at UC Riverside

*April 2010* 

**VOLUNTEER** 

Society of Women Engineers at UC Riverside

Engineering Day Yearly 2009 - 2015

### = PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS ==

**MATERIALS ADVANTAGE** 

Member

**UC Riverside Student Chapter** 

2016 – present

**SOCIETY OF WOMEN ENGINEERS** 

Professional-Collegiate Liasone

Professional Work-Life Balance Chair

**Orange County Professional Chapter** 

2015 - 2016

2014 - 2015

**SOCIETY OF WOMEN ENGINEERS** 

President

Professional Development Officer

**UC Riverside Student Chapter** 

2010 - 2011

2009 - 2010